Guide to the Richard Hooker Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Richard Hooker papers
1907-1964
MS 697
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
Correspondence with political figures, particularly documenting Hooker's role as adviser and friend to several presidents.
Hooker, Richard, 1878-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Originally given by Richard Hooker with the Samuel Bowles Papers as the Bowles-Hooker Collection, in 1963-1964; separated into the Hooker Papers and the Bowles Papers in 1979.
Biographical / Historical
Richard Hooker, journalist, was born in Augusta, Georgia, on 20 February 1878, the son of Thomas and Sarah Augustus (Bowles) Hooker. He received his B.A. from Yale in 1899, after which he spent a year studying in Europe. Soon after his return he joined the staff of the Springfield Republican, the newspaper founded by his great-grandfather, Samuel Bowles I, in 1824. He was Washington correspondent from 1904 to 1911, literary editor from 1911 to 1915, and editor-in-chief from 1915 to 1922. He resigned from the editorship because of poor health in 1922 and became president of the Republican Company, which position he retained until 1932. He directed the Associated Press between 1927 and 1934.
During his newspaper career, Hooker was associated with several United States presidents. Taft offered to make him White House press secretary, and Wilson chose him for assistant secretary of the treasury, but he declined both appointments.
Hooker married Winifred Eells Newberry on 31 December 1910. They had four children: Richard, Sarah Paige, Mary Newberry, and Arthur Bowles. Richard Hooker died on 25 November 1967.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Richard Hooker Papers consist of slightly less than a hundred letters exchanged with various men of greater and lesser importance in twentieth-century American politics. The major historical interest of this correspondence is that it documents Hooker's relationship with several presidents as adviser and friend. Among the subjects are these: Harding's position on the League of Nations (Winthrop Murray Crane, 19 July 1920), Hoover's candidacy for the presidency (Hooker to Hoover, 24 July 1928), Wilson's aspirations for the U.S. Navy (Hooker to Wilson, 5 February 1916), the political activities of Frank B. Brandegee (Hooker to Taft, 21 October 1919), the Electoral College (George W. Norris, 6 June 1944; Hooker and Mark Sullivan, 14 June-12 July 1944), second-class postal rates (Hooker and Wilson, 1 May-1 June 1918, undated), and the Cambridge subway bill (Calvin Coolidge, 16 December 1919 and 31 December 1924).
Arrangement
the papers are arrnged alphabetically by correspondent.
Journalism -- Political aspects; Journalism; New England; United States -- Politics and government; Journalists; Baker, Ray Stannard, 1870-1946; Baruch, Bernard M. (Bernard Mannes), 1870-1965; Bowles, Samuel, 1826-1878; Churchill, Winston, 1874-1965; Colby, Bainbridge, 1869-1950; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933; Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948; Hooker, Richard, 1878-; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948; Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930; Wilson, Edith Bolling Galt, 1872-1961; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924
- Baker, Ray Stannard, 1937 January 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Baruch, Bernard M., 1940 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bowles, Samuel [III], 1907 December 20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Churchill, Winston, 1964 November 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Colby, Bainbridge, 1920 August 9 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Cook, Waldo S., Circa 1926 July (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Coolidge, Calvin, 1919, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Crane, Winthrop Murray, (1853-1920), 1920 May-August (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Crane, Winthrop Murray (1881-), 1944 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Daniels, Josephus, 1945 March 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Hadley, Arthur T., 1920 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Herrick, Myron T., 1927 June 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Herter, Christian A., 1920 September 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Hoover, Herbert C., 1920-1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Hughes, Charles E., 1927, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Hull, Cordell, 1944 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Link, Arthur S., 1961 November 28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Norris, George W., 1944 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Roosevelt, Franklin, 1941 February 12 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Seymour, Charles, 1942 June 11 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Sullivan, Mark, 1944 June (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Taft, Charles P., 1963 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Taft, William Howard, 1919-1924 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Underwood, Oscar W., 1921 October 19 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Wilson, Edith Bolling Galt, 1924-1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Wilson, Woodrow, 1916-1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)